Guide to the American Left Ephemera Collection, 1875-2015 AIS.2007.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
American Left Ephemera Collection
1875-2015
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Oestreicher, Richard Jules
AIS.2007.11
22.75 Linear Feet (37 boxes)
Dr. Richard Oestreicher, Associate Professor of History at the University of Pittsburgh, amassed the American Left Ephemera Collection over a 35-year period to document the history of the American Left from the 1870s to the present. Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
Accruals
Received a second donation of material in November 2014 and a third in December 2015.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Richard Oestreicher on October 2, 2008.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by subject into 28 series; the list is arranged by type.
Series I. African Americans and the Left
Series II. Anarchists
Series III. Anti-War Propaganda
Series IV. Christian Socialism
Series V. Citizens Party
Series VI. Communists and Civil Liberties
Series VII. Communist Party USA (CPUSA)
Series VIII. Ethnic Radicalism
Series IX. Feminism, Gay and Lesbian
Series X. Labor
Series XI. Leftist Organizations Thought in Relation to the Rest of the World and U.S. Economics/Imperialism
Series XII. New Left Organizations
Series XIII. Other Radical/Leftist Organizations
Series XIV. Popular Front Culture
Series XV. Progressive Party
Series XVI. Socialist Labor Party (SLP)
Series XVII. Socialist Party USA (SPUSA)
Series XVIII. Socialist Worker's Party (SWP)
Series XIX. Students for a Democratic Society (SDS)
Series XX. Student Peace Union (SPU)
Series XXI. Utopian Socialism
Series XXII. Vietnam War
Series XXIII. Realia: Pins and Other Objects
Series XXIV. Twenty-First Century Radical Movements
Series XXV. Democratic Socialism
Series XXVI. Food Not Bombs
Series XXVII. Populists/Pre-Populists
Series XXVIII. Radical Academics
Related Material
A.E. Forbes Communist Collection, 1921-1972, AIS.2000.07, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Custodial History
In Oestreicher's own words, "In graduate school I discovered that the world of antique ephemera and collectibles gave me access to historical raw materials and a source of supplementary income. Selling junk was more fun and more lucrative than other jobs that had carried me through summer breaks in graduate funding. For the last thirty-four years I've followed a sometimes schizophrenic path: radical historian by day, hippy-trippy, petty bourgeois capitalist on the side. Along the way I accumulated a vast hoard of ephemera relating to American working-class and radical history." Oestreicher donated his collection to the Archives Service Center in 2007.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection includes items from the 1870s to the present including periodicals, photographs, letters, pamphlets, books, posters, flyers, labels, pins and other objects, but it emphasizes ephemeral items (e.g., items made for one time or brief usage and then likely to be discarded). While the majority of these items were produced by the Socialist Party USA (SPUSA), Communist Party USA (CPUSA), Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), or organizations linked to them, the collection also includes material from a wide variety of other organizations and movements as well as from unaffiliated activists and radical intellectuals.
Dr. Richard Oestreicher wrote all of the scope and content notes within the collection as well as writing the History section.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
History
The Left
Left and Right as political designations date to the French Revolution when the Jacobins sat on the left in the National Assembly and the Girondins on the right. The Left has come to mean movements, organizations, and intellectual or cultural tendencies that emphasize an egalitarian ethos, a utopian vision of social reconstruction, and a commitment to agitation and action to advance that ethos and vision.
Major Left-Wing Organizations in the Twentieth-Century U.S.
Only three left-wing organizations have attained mass followings in the twentieth-century U.S.: the Socialist Party of the U.S. (SPUSA), the Communist Party of the U.S. (CPUSA), and the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS). Founded 1901 with remnants still in existence today, SPUSA reached a peak membership of about 120,000 around the 1912 election when it polled 6% of the presidential vote. The party declined sharply after 1919 from a combination of government repression, a split between reformists and revolutionaries crystallized by the Bolshevik revolution, and the effects of social change on their core constituencies and on the credibility of their hopes for imminent change.
CPUSA, formed out of an amalgamation of revolutionary factions from the 1919 split in the Socialist Party, reached a membership of roughly 75,000 (with a pool of close sympathizers, "fellow travelers," perhaps five to ten times larger than the membership) at the end of the 1930s and again during WWII. CPUSA declined very rapidly after the war under the impact of the Cold War, disillusionment with the Soviet Union, postwar prosperity, and the Party's dogmatic and sectarian tendencies.
SDS began as the student wing of the League for Industrial Democracy (originally an organization of socialist college students that evolved into a social-democratic policy group of intellectuals and union functionaries). They parted company with the parent organization over Vietnam and anticommunism in the early 1960s, and expanded rapidly during the 1960s as the most visible American exponents of the New Left. In contrast to the old Left parties, SDS did not collect monthly dues or keep systematic membership records, so estimates of its membership vary widely, but at its peak in 1968-69 probably several hundred thousand people identified themselves at least loosely with SDS.
Role of the Left in Modern U.S. History
Although each of these organizations briefly functioned as a mass movement, none sustained substantial organization for much more than a decade. Nonetheless, they had decisive impact on modern American history. Left-wing activists played crucial roles in virtually every progressive social movement in twentieth-century America: labor organization, civil rights and black liberation, antiwar and peace movements, feminism, gay rights, environmentalism, and anti-globalism. They shaped terms of debate in American political culture and forced mainstream politicians to respond to their arguments. Understanding the history of the Left is thus critical to understanding key themes in American history.
Previous Citation
American Left Ephemera Collection, 1875-2015, AIS.2007.11, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Communism -- United States -- History -- Sources; New Left -- United States -- History -- Sources; Radicalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Minorities -- Political activity -- United States -- Sources; Utopian socialism -- United States -- History -- Sources; Anarchism -- United States -- History -- Sources; Posters; Pamphlets; Buttons (Information artifacts); Photographs; Labor -- United States -- History -- Sources; Social action; Politics; Christian socialism -- United States -- History -- Sources; Socialism -- United States -- History -- Sources; Student Peace Union (U.S.) -- History -- Sources; Socialist Workers Party -- History -- Sources; Socialist Labor Party -- History -- Sources; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.) -- History -- Sources; Communist Party of the United States of America -- History -- Sources; Socialist Party (U.S.) -- History -- Sources
- African Americans and the Left, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series focuses on the role African Americans played in leftist movements and on left wing support for campaigns against racist practices and for Black civil rights, including the major role Communism played in the Civil Rights Movement before the 1950s, and influence of Black Liberation on the New Left. While the Socialist Party gave nominal rhetorical support to racial equality, most Socialist Party leaders considered racial discrimination (or gender, ethnic, or religious discrimination) as distinctly secondary to the class struggle, and a significant minority within the Party harbored racist views. Blacks folks suffered, SP leaders argued, primarily because their labor was exploited and that would only be solved by socialism.
  Communists, in contrast, stressed the importance of racial discrimination, saw combatting racism as a prerequisite to progress on all other issues, and insisted on individual personal commitment to antiracism as a non-negotiable part of adherence to Party discipline. While advocacy by Black activists contributed to this posture, it resulted primarily from positions developed within the Communist International (Comintern) and pushed by key Soviet leaders such as Lenin and Stalin. Communists considered the problems of African-Americans as a special case of what they called the "national question," that is the national aspirations of ethnic groups and peoples suffering discrimination and denial of rights because of their domination within colonial empires or within multi-ethnic European Empires such as the German, Austro-Hungarian, and Russian Empires. Communist concern with the national question derived mainly from two influences. First, the Soviet state incorporated the many discontented national groups of the Russian Empire forcing Soviet leaders to develop a national policy. They responded by creating a series of nominally independent ethnic republics or autonomous regions and reinventing the state as a theoretically egalitarian union of these republics. Second, Communists considered the massive popular discontent of colonial peoples as the Achilles heel of world capitalism and a great political opportunity to expand their global influence. Soviet and Comintern efforts attracted the attention of many prominent anticolonial leaders including a group of Black intellectuals who developed to develop the ideal and program of Pan-Africanism. While many Pan-Africanists eventually became disillusioned with Communism, this overlap between Communism and Pan-Africanism had enduring influence on Black nationalists within the United States into the 1960s even after the CPUSA ceased to be an even minimally viable organization.
  New Left concern with civil rights and Black liberation derived first from the inspirational role of the Civil Rights movement, and second from the way the US participation in the War in Vietnam made activists aware of the problems of colonialism, imperialism, and relationships between developed and underdeveloped countries. New Leftists, inspired by Pan-Africanism (in some cases without full awareness of the history of these formulations) tended to think of African-Americans as a colonial people marooned within in the imperialist metropole.
  - Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) Flyer (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Songs of the Southern Freedom Movement, We Shall Overcome! compiled by Guy and Candie Carawan for The Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Truth About Columbia Tennessee Cases (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Three Associated Press Photographs of African American Communist Angelo Herndon, Mid 1930's (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jim Crow "Justice" In Korea, The Case of Lieutenant Leon Gilbert (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - In Defense of Negro Rights, by Benjamin J. Davis, January 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Negro People in the struggle for Peace and Freedom, By Benjamin J. Davis, February 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Negro People on the March, Report to the National Committee of the Communist Party, U.S.A., by Benjamin J. Davis, August 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Historic Fight to Abolish School Segregation in the United States, by Doxey A. Wilkerson (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Negro Question", Outline and Study-Guide for Five-Session Course, January 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Negro History Week, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Negro History Week, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Negro History Week, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Negro History Week, February 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Umbra, December, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Umbra Anthology, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - This Man Will Die Unless You Help (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Cruel and Unusual Punishment of Henry Winston, by Mike Newberry (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Resolutions from the American Negro Leadership Conference on Africa", September 24-27, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The White Problem (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letter from Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., April 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Memo to contributors from the SCLC Staff, April 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Negroes Beaten in Grenada School Integration" New York Times article, Tuesday, September 13, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Michael Zinzun for the 55th Assembly District campaign pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Black Party Founding Convention" flyer, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Hear the Communist Candidates" flyer (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Hot Thang---Bar-B-Q" Flyer, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The Road to Liberation for the Negro People, September 1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Rally For Youth Rights" Flyer (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Justice For All Humanity, Colored America Answers the Challenge of Pearl S. Buck (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Africa Fights for Freedom, by Alphaeus Hunton, March 1950 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - David P. Widamen For Congress 4th Congressional District Progressive Party Ticket Campaign Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Vote for a Fighter against War and Racism, Jarvis Tyner, Communist Candidate for Vice-President (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Theoretical Aspects of the Negro Question in the United States" (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The New Secession- And How To Smash It, Riding to Freedom, by Herbert Aptheker and James E. Jackson, June 1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Forces of Progress in the South, Workers, Farmers, and the Negro People, by Jim Jackson, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - American Imperialism and White Chauvinism, by Herbert Aptheker (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - FEPC, How it was Betrayed, How it can be Saved, By Rob Fowler Hall, February 1950 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "The Time is Now! Mr. President Wipe Out Slums and Ghettos! Billions for Life-Not Death!" Open Letter (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Program to End Ghettos and Fight Poverty" Flyer (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - The Road to Negro Liberation, Report to the Eighth Convention of the Communist Party of the U.S.A., by Harry Haywood, June 1934 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Some Aspects of the Negro Question in the United States, by James E. Jackson, July 1959 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Now is the Time, by M.E. Travis (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Let Freedom Ride the Rails (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Negro Freedom is in the Interest of Every American, by Gus Hall, July 1964 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - The Party of Negro and White, By Pettis Perry, March, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Marxism and Negro Liberation, by Gus Hall, May 1951 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "Marxism and the Negro Question" (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - American Negro Problems (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - The Struggle for Afro-American Liberation (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Negro Representation Now!, by Elaine Ross (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - The Communist Position on the Negro Question (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - On Certain Aspects of Bourgeois Nationalism Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Negro-White Unity, by Henry Winston, February 1967 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - For These Things We Fight Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - The Jobless Negro, by Elizabeth Lawson (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Black Coal Miners in the United States, by Paul Nyden (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - The People Versus Segregated Schools, by Doxey A. Wilkerson, February 1955 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - The Jerry Newson Story..., by Buddy Green and Steve Murdock, October 1950 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Behind the Florida Bombings, Who Killed NAACP Leader Harry T. Moore and his wife?, by Joseph North, February 1952 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Behind the Lynching of Emmet Louis Till, by Louis Burnham, December 1955 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - The Killing of William Milton, by Art Shields, September 1948 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Lynching and Frame-Up in Tennessee, by Robert Minor, October 1946 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Stop Police Brutality, March 1952 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - The Position of Negro Women, by Eugene Gordon and Cyril Briggs, February 1935 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - The Communist Part and the Emancipation of the Negro People, by Earl Browder (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - "Theoretical Aspects of the Negro Question in the United States" (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - "Henry Winston Meets Angela Davis", by Gene Tournour (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - The Negro Today, by Herbert Aptheker, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - The Story of Discrimination in Government Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - The Shadow of the South is On Our Shops! Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - "Who are the Friends of the Negro People?", by C.A. Hathaway (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Official Proceedings of the Second All-Southern Negro Youth Conference, May 1938 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Democracy vs. Force and Violence! (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - "Negro Workers! White Workers! Organize and Fight Against Lynching!" Flyer, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - The Communist Position on the Negro Question, February 1947 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - World Problems of the Negro People (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Negro Representation- A Step Towards Negro Freedom, by Pettis Perry, March 1952 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - The Government Takes a Hand in the Cotton-Patch, by George Anstrom, November 1933 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - The Legacy of Slavery and the Roots of Black Nationalism, by Eugene D. Genovese (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - On the Struggle for Peace and Freedom, by Benjamin J. Davis, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - "Call for Truth! To Silence Racist Ravings" (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - "Make the March a Million Strong!" (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - "Bibliography on the Negro Question", June 1950 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Black Workers in Revolt Pamphlet, by Robert Dudnick (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - The General Policy Statement and Labor Program of the League of Revolutionary Black Workers (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Eldon Ave. Revolutionary Union Movement Pamphlets (2) (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - El Rum Pamphlets (4) (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Uni Rum Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Me Rum Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Frum Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - League of Revolutionary Black Workers on Repression Speech, by Kenneth Cockrel (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - To the Point...Of Production, An Interview with John Watson (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - "Core Demands to Board of Education", September 3, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Spear: Who is James Johnson Pamphlet, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Spear, V.1, N.1, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Drum: Wildcat Strike, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Drum: Challenge, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Drum: Drum's Candidate, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Drum: Hoover Road, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Drum: Lily White--Super Right, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Drum: The Root of Racism, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Drum: What Has Drum Done?, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Drum: All Out in the Wash, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Drum Hail James Johnson, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Drum: Walter Reuther is Dead and So is the U.A.W. Contract, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Cooley High Black Student Voice, November 5, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Black Student Voice: "Black Voice of Revolution", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - "Elect Claude Lightfoot" Flyer, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - The Spirit of George Jackson Pamphlet, September 1972 (Box 1, Folder 110, Unknown item 11)
  - Why Negroes Should oppose the War Pamphlet, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Printed Invitation to 23rd Testimonial Dinner of the Los Angeles Committee for the Defense of the Bill of Rights, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Invitation to 20th Annual Banquet of the Los Angeles Committee for the Defense of the Bill of Rights, October 20, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - "Save Fletcher Mills" Flyer, June 13, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Dixie Comes to New York: Story of the Freeport GI Slayings Pamphlet, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - The Monroe Kidnapping Newsletter, November 1961 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Vigilante Terror in Fontana: The Tragic Story of O'Day H. Short and His Family Pamphlet, February 1946 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - "From Lynch Threat to Frame-Up" Flyer (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - "For Immediate Release" memo, October 15 1970 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Special Report, Lunch- Counter Desegregation in Corpus Christi, Galveston, and San Antonio, Texas, by Kenneth Moreland, May 10, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Unfinished Revolution, by Tom Kahn, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - From Protest to Politics: The Future of the Civil Rights Movement, by Bayard Rustin, February 1965 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Flyer advertising a demonstration referred to as the "Mass Funeral" (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Vote Negroes Into Office" Flyer (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Parade and Demonstrate" Flyer (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - History of the American Negro People, 1619-1918, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "International Black Workers Congress" Draft Proposal (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "Young Negro Workers! Fight Against Bosses Wars!" Flyer for youth rally (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - "The Negro People in the United States, Facts for all Americans", 1953 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Inner-City Voice, April 1, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Inner-City Voice, July 15, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Inner-City Voice, November-December, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Inner-City Voice, February, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Assorted Information Regarding the Various Protests of Black Workers (Detroit Automobile Factory Workers in Particular) (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Assorted Information Regarding Black Revolutionary Activities (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Assorted Information Regarding Black Revolutionary Activities (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Take Howard Out of the National Student Federation (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - A Call for a Petition Campaign and Youth March (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - "Guilty of Being a Negro" (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Ernestine L. Rose, "Her Address on the Anniversary of West Indian Emancipation", 1949 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Coming! W.E.B. DuBois (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Los Angeles Congress of Racial Equality Active membership Bulletin (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Angela Davis Newsletter (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - All Night Vigil, October 24, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - "Free Angela Davis" Flyer, ca. 1971 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - "Calendar of a Frame-Up" Flyer, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - "People Against Racism" Newsletter, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - "My Friends" Native Son, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - "Serve The People" Black Panther Flyer, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - "Don't Buy At Thriftmart", ca. 1964 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - "The Worker's Council", June 1921 (Box 20, Folder 65)
  - Paul Robeson AP Wire Photos (8), 1949-1963 (Box 20, Folder 66)
  - "Paul Robeson Soviet-American Friendship Rally" 1 photo, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 67)
  - "Paul Robeson: Artist and Citizen" Brochure, September 1999 (Box 20, Folder 68)
  - "Scottsboro Boys Press Photos" (2), July 1937 (Box 20, Folder 69)
  - "Judge Horton and the Scottsboro Boys" Photos (3), 1976 (Box 20, Folder 70)
  - "The Committee of 100": 4 letters, 3 pamphlets, 1946-1948 (Box 20, Folder 71)
  - US ex rel. Winnifred Lynn v. Downer" Petition to Supreme Court, 1943 (Box 20, Folder 72)
  - "United Front for Panther Defense" Flyer, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 73)
  - William Kunster Speaking for the San Quentin Six- Poster with Photo, 1971 (Box 20, Folder 74)
  - "Denmark Vesey: A Modern Dramatic Oratorio" Program, February 1961 (Box 20, Folder 75)